Guide to the Paul Oppermann papers, 1926-1964
Oppermann, Paul papers, 1926-1964
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Paul Oppermann papers, 1926-1964.
3161
Paul Oppermann, 1903-.
2 cubic ft.
Correspondence, speeches, papers, scrapbooks.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence between Alfred Bettman and officials of the Federal Housing Administration; findings of committees; reports; legislative acts; proposals; agenda; proceedings of the Conference on City Planning Administration in Chicago; correspondence as Director of City Planning, City and County of San Francisco and of the Northeastern Illinois Metropolitan Area Planning Commission; speeches; and scrapbooks.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
City planner and planning consultant.
In the 1940s, Oppermann advised on federal housing legislation as a planner for the Federal Housing Administration. He was planning director of San Francisco city and county from 1949-58, and was the first director of the Illinois planning agency, predecessor to the Northeastern Illinois Planning Commission. He served as president of the American Institute of Planners and as assistant director of the American Society of Planning Officials. Oppermann lectured in metropolitan planning at Massachusetts Institute of Technology. He was a member of the International Fraternity of Lambda Alpha, Ely Chapter.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes carbon typescripts of correspondence between Alfred Bettman and officials of the Federal Housing Administration, with copies directed to Oppermann; memoranda; findings of committees; reports and drafts; legislative acts; notes; proposals; agenda; studies; published proceedings of the Conference on City Planning Administration in Chicago, 1936; correspondence as Director of City Planning, City and County of San Francisco and as Director of the Northeastern Illinois Metropolitan Area Planning Commission; speeches, 1926-1964; and scrapbooks.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Oppermann, Paul, 1903-.; Bettman, Alfred, 1873-1945.; Lambda Alpha International.Ely Chapter.; Northeastern Illinois Metropolitan Area Planning Commission.; United States. Federal Housing Administration.; Conference on City Planning Administration(1936:Chicago)
Subjects:
City planning.; City planning--Illinois.; City planning--California--San Francisco.; Housing authorities.; Housing policy.; City planners.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Part of Lambda Alpha Literary Archives.
CONTAINER LIST
- Urban Redevelopment Law, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Correspondence on Program of the Committee on Housing and Blighted Areas, deteriorated districts, real estate assessment, causes of blight, population density, technological change, rapid transportation systems, land tenure and land use institutions, building codes, real estate mortgage system, loans and grants, public ownership of blight areas, interdependence of rural and urban economy. Includes Philip H. Cornick, Frederick Bigger, Frederic A. Delano, Earle Sumner Draper, National Resources Planning Board, Committee on Housing and Blighted Areas, National Association of Real Estate Boards.
- Urban Redevelopment Law, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 2, 3, 4)
  Correspondence and drafts on Federal Agencies, U.S. Housing Act, terminology advantages and disadvantages of combination of existing agencies, City Realty Corporations, tax delinquency, Urban Redevelopment Corporations, amortizations, FHA staff activities, Decentralization study, urban population patterns, municipal fiscal instability, FHA policy limitations, planning agency, land acquisition agency, obsolete neighborhood demolition, municipal bonding, Decentralization study brochure, zoning and subdivision regulations, industry distribution patterns, essential elements for federal urban redevelopment legislation, community automony vs. federal control, Professor Hansen, planning stages, provisions of the new draft housing investment insurance. Includes Alfred Bettman, Frederick Bigger, Paul Oppermann, Herbert S. Colton, Earle Sumner Draper, Federal Agency of Urban Reconstruction and Development Committee to Examine and Report on Cornick's Decentralization Study, Federal Housing Administration, Department of Urban Affairs.
- Urban Redevelopment Law, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 5, 6)
  Correspondence, reports, drafts on terminology, provisions of the Urban Redevelopment Act, federal agencies, district boundaries, development vs. redevelopment, program for city building and urban housing, city growth forecasts, Urban Land Institute Bill, population data use. Includes Herbert S. Colton, Alfred Bettman, Frederick Bigger, E. S. Draper, Alvin H. Hansen, Martin Myerson, National Housing Administration, Work Projects Administration, Federal Security Agency, American Society of Planning Officials.
- Urban Redevelopment Law, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Correspondence, reports on urban and regional planning technique, population planning, land use planning, circulatory planning, city functions, urban complex study. Includes Alvin H. Hansen, Charles S. Ascher, Communities Redevelopment Corporation.
- Bibliography of Collection Holdings, July 31, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- American Institute of Planners. Committee on Education and Personnel Standards. Agenda for Discussion, Annual Meeting., Jan. 22, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- American Society of Planning Officials. Proceedings of the Conference on City Planning and Administration. Chicago, Ill., 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Oppermann, Paul. "The Replanning and Rebuilding of Our Central Cities.", Sept. 11, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Paper presented before City Planning Division, Centennial Conference of the American Society of Civil Engineers, Chicago, Ill.
- Oppermann, Paul. "A Planner's View of Express Highways." Research Board, Washington, D.C., Dec. 3, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Oppermann, Paul. "Should Your Child be a City and Regional Planner?" Saturday Evening Post, pp. 44-45. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Oppermann, Paul. Progress Report Tri-Cities Planning Project. Report to the City Planning Commissions of Bristol, Johnson City, and Kingsport., Feb. 12, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letters from Bureau of Facilities, Federal Works, and re appointment as Director of Planning in San Francisco., 1930-1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Letters from Bureau of Facilities, Federal Works, and re appointment as Director of Planning in San Francisco., 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Primarily thank you notes as Director of the Department of City Planning., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Letters as Director of City Planning, San Francisco., 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Letters of congratulations re appointment to Northeastern Illinois Metropolitan Area Planning Commission., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence re appointment to Northeastern Illinois Metropolitan Area Planning Commission., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Letters as Executive Director of the Northeastern Illinois Metropolitan Area Planning Commission., 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Letter as Director of Northeastern Illinois Metropolitan Area Planning Commission., 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Scrapbook of newspaper clippings., 1950-1954
- Scrapbook of newspaper clippings., 1952-1958
- Scrapbook of newspaper clippings., 1958-1959
- Scrapbook of newspaper clippings., 1955-1963
- Certificates (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Clippings (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Photographs (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Speeches, 1926-1936 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Speeches, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Speeches, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Speeches, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Speeches, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Speeches, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Speeches, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Speeches, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Speeches, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Speeches, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Speeches, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Speeches, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Speeches, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Speeches, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Speeches, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Speeches, Feb. 1955 - June 1955 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Speeches, Sept. 1955 - Oct. 1955 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Speeches, Jan. 1956 - Mar. 1956 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Speeches, Apr. 1956 - Sept. 1956 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Speeches, Oct. 1956- Dec. 1956 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Speeches, Jan. 1958 - May 1958 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Speeches, June 1958 - Aug. 1958 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Speeches, Sept. 1958 - Dec. 1958 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Speeches, May 1959 - June 1959 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Speeches, Jan. 1959 - Feb. 1959 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Speeches, Mar. 1959 - Apr. 1959 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Speeches, July 1959 - Sept. 1959 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Speeches, Oct. 1959 - Dec. 1959 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Speeches, Jan. 1960 - May 1960 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Speeches, June 1960 - Dec. 1960 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Speeches, Jan. 1961 - Apr. 1961 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Speeches, June 1961 - Nov. 1961 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Speeches, Jan. 1962 - Mar. 1962 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Speeches, Apr. 1962 - June 1962 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Speeches, July 1962 - Sept. 1962 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Speeches, Oct. 1962 - Dec. 1962 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Speeches, Feb. 1963 - June 1963 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Speeches, July 1963 - Jan. 1964 (Box 2, Folder 41)